<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title></title>
 <link href="http://dangeng.github.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://dangeng.github.io/blog/"/>
 <updated>2020-05-05T03:39:02-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://dangeng.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Daniel Geng</name>
   <email>berkeleymarriagepact@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>The Social Networks of College Campuses</title>
   <link href="http://dangeng.github.io/2020/05/05/social-networks/"/>
   <updated>2020-05-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://dangeng.github.io/blog/2020/05/05/social-networks</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a longish post, so here’s a TL;DR and links to the highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;./#scraper&quot;&gt; We build a scraper (against Instagram’s Terms of Service) to map social networks.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The social network of Berkeley is &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; racially segregated.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;./#clusters&quot;&gt;There are distinct “asian,” “white,” “black,” “athlete,” “freshman,” “sophomore,” and “greek life” clusters.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;./#srats&quot;&gt;You can see the “tiers” of Berkeley’s sororities, with the “tier” rising with growing racial homogeneity.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;./#largeschools&quot;&gt;We look at other schools to see if they also have “implicit segregation.” Our hot take: “implicit segregation” is a result of large schools.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;./#method&quot;&gt; We talk about our methodology in a bit more depth.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the things here are to some extent “common knowledge” but I think it’s interesting that we can give some sort of empirical, objective evidence for these phenomena. If anybody knows of prior work in this area (I would be highly surprised if I were the first to look into this) please let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scraper&quot;&gt;Violating Instagram’s Terms of Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s something interesting about Instagram. It turns out if you follow anybody whose account is public, &lt;em&gt;even if your account is private&lt;/em&gt; you will show up on their “followers list” available for the entire world to see. This fact makes Instagram an incredibly attractive platform to scrape for social networks, which is exactly what we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is of course against Instagram’s Terms of Service, as per “General Conditions” section 8:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We prohibit crawling, scraping, caching or otherwise accessing any content on the Service via automated means, including but not limited to, user profiles and photos&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-scraper&quot;&gt;The Scraper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The details of the scraper aren’t terribly important, so I won’t bore you with the nitty gritty details. But for completeness I’ll give a brief description here (feel free to skip to the next section). Let’s say we’re scraping Berkeley’s network. Essentially we do a priority search starting with a few people we know for sure are in Berkeley, where priority is assigned as “the number of times we’ve seen this username in the list of followers of someone we are fairly sure is from Berkeley.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does “fairly sure is from Berkeley” mean? Well, we found it simple enough to look for certain keywords in a user’s Instagram bio such as “Cal” or “Berkeley” or “Go Bears” (it’s a rather nice fluke that the majority of people seem to insist on identifying which college they go to in their Instagram bio). Using this rather simple method we actually get a really decent scraper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please see the &lt;a href=&quot;./#method&quot;&gt;methods section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-overview-of-berkeley&quot;&gt;An Overview of Berkeley&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first scraped Berkeley. Using our scraper we get the usernames of people who go to Berkeley, who they follow, and how many “hearts” they get per post. Here is the social network plotted out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/graph/users_aug_small.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Berkeley's social network. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are about 30,000 colored specks in the graph, each corresponding to an Instagram user who attends or has attended UC Berkeley (at least, with high probability). The thin wispy lines indicate connections between users. The location of the nodes are chosen so that users with common connections are closer to each other (using ForceAtlas2) and the specks are sized according to average likes per post and are colored according to “social group.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These “social groups” are found by running an unsupervised clustering algorithm on the graph. Surprisingly, these automatically detected clusters correspond incredibly well to real social groups!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point you might have all sorts of questions about the rigor of this analysis, so for more information please checkout the &lt;a href=&quot;./#method&quot;&gt;methods section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clusters&quot;&gt;Social Groups of Berkeley&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/graph/annotated.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Berkeley's social network, annotated. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we’ve annotated roughly what each social group each color corresponds to. It’s actually quite remarkable just how racial these clusters ended up being. Of course people can be part of multiple social groups, but these clusters are striking for their absolute uniformity. For example, sampling people from the “athlete” cluster almost always ends up with an athlete, while sampling outside the “athlete” cluster almost never results in an athlete. Within the “racial” clusters we get some 70% - 80% homogeneity! (Again, the &lt;a href=&quot;./#method&quot;&gt;methods section&lt;/a&gt; has more info).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering how we can be sure what each group is. Well, we can do two things. First off, we can parse each user’s bio (which quite frequently contains very useful identifying information such as “college attended,” “graduation year,” and “frat or sorority”). For example, parsing user summaries for graduation year and superimposing the years on the graph we see that the cyan and light green clusters almost exclusively have years “23” and “22” (along with “19” and “18” for the corresponding high school graduation dates):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;table style=&quot;width=100%&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/graph/freshmen.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Freshmen (primarily 19 and 23) &lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/graph/sophomores.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Sophomores (primarily 18 and 22) &lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same sort of strategy works to identify various fraternities and sororities as we’ll see in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And secondly, we can do the naive thing and just literally look at (stalk) the users in each social group. This is of course less desirable, but I think it gets the job done. We resort to this strategy when labeling the clusters with a certain type of race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be curious about what sorts of accounts are in each cluster. I don’t think I should list personal Instagram accounts here (even if they’re public), but I think listing professional or organization accounts should be alright:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asian Frat/Srat (“rave slaves”)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/imneukkim/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;imneukkim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/alvinbobo/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;alvinbobo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/jstn.chng/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;jstn.chng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/berkeleysigmas/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;berkeleysigmas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asians
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/afxdance/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;afxdance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/afxcomp/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;afxcomp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/ucbmovement/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ucbmovement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/main_stacks/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;main_stacks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/calblackalumni/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;calblackalumni&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/gammaalphanupes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gammaalphanupes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/unitedtribesof_africa/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;unitedtribesof_africa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/africanstudents.berkeley/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;africanstudents.berkeley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;White
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/berkeleyhillel/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;berkeleyhillel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/student__action/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;student__action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Bottom” Tier Sororities
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/caltridelta/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;caltridelta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/ztacal/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ztacal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/caltheta/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;caltheta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Upper” Tier Sororities
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/caldeltagamma/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;caldeltagamma &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/calalphaphi/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;calalphaphi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/calkappa/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;calkappa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Athletes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/amybilquist/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;amybilquist&lt;/a&gt; (swimmer)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/kristine__31/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;kristine__31&lt;/a&gt; (WBNA)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/thekid.da/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;thekid.da&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/rayraydavison/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;rayraydavison&lt;/a&gt; (Kansas City Chiefs)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/chadhansen6/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;chadhansen6&lt;/a&gt; (Houston Texans)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;srats&quot;&gt;Social Hierarchies in Sororities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section we’ll talk about the sororities at Berkeley. Sororities are nice to look at because so many sorority sisters are active on Instagram and seem to love to publicize their greek letters in their bios. This is as opposed to fraternity brothers who seem to be much less active on Instagram and tend not to put anything useful in their bios (at least, not useful to us!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s zoom into the “greek life” area of the social network. Here I’ve labeled the sororities that various users are associated with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/graph/greek_annotated_2.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Zoomed in and annotated &quot;greek life&quot; cluster. Approximate vertical centroid of various sororities listed on the right. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice right away that this area of the graph is a lot more colorful! This is (at least it seems to me) because people in greek life tend to be very clique-y. In fact, the clustering algorithm seems to actually be able to cluster individual sororities. For example, Zeta is a dark green, near the top. Alpha Phi is pink, near the bottom. And Kappa Kappa Gamma is a dark purple also near the bottom. What’s crazy is that this clustering has predictive power: we can actually guess what sororities people are in, even if they don’t mention it in their summary and even if their account is private!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also told by a friend who knows about these things that the order in which the sororities appear in the image seem to be ordered almost exactly according to their “tier.” For example, Alpha Phi, Kappa, and Pi Phi are the “highest-tier” sororities and they all appear clustered together at the bottom. The cluster at the top of the image are apparently “lower tier” sororities, consisting of people from Tri Delta, Zeta, Theta, and others. In addition, it’s interesting to note that diversity seems to decrease in the same direction as increasing “tier” (in general, the further away from the center of the social network the less diverse). Interesting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know much about sororities, but based on the image alone I would hazard a hypothesis that there are perhaps two different groups of sororities which both keep mostly to themselves. One group being “lower-tier” but more diverse and the other group being “higher-tier” but less diverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-gradual-segregation-of-berkeley&quot;&gt;The Gradual Segregation of Berkeley&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might have noticed that there’s a “freshman” and a “sophomore” cluster but there’s no “junior” or “senior” cluster. Here’s a hypothesis I have about why that’s the case. When people start school in Berkeley they are forced to hang out with their dorm-mates and their floor, people essentially randomly selected (except for maybe your roommate). So everybody becomes friends with everybody on their floor, and the floor above and below them, and you get this big cluster of freshmen in your social network. The next year people move out of the dorms and start making their own friends by themselves and enter new social circles. So the group of sophomores shrinks and the other social groups expand (this is why the cyan cluster of  freshmen is larger than the light green cluster of sophomores, even though we expect roughly the same number of sophomores as freshmen!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, most people find their own circle of friends completely unrelated to their random floor assignment in freshman year and consequently there’s no “junior” or “senior” cluster. In fact, we can superimpose a sort of “time” or an “age” axis on the social network to make this a bit more obvious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/graph/annotated_2.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Don't take the axis too literally! &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that despite the fact people start college in a diverse social group, they tend to segregate themselves out into homogenous clusters of friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;largeschools&quot;&gt;Implicit Segregation at Large Schools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berkeley does a lot to promote diversity, but it can only do so much. Once freshman year is over and the assigned dorms are gone the university can hardly force people to hang out with diverse friends, and it shows. The only non-racial social groups are the dance community and the athletes (except, both are still rather racially segregated, with the dance community being primarily asian and the athletes being white). One might ask &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; this happens. Perhaps we can look at other schools. Here is UCLA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/graph/ucla_annotated.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;The leftmost offshoot is a cluster of black &quot;influencers&quot; (or something to that effect, I honestly can't tell) that are associated with the general LA area and seem to have a large pull on the UCLA community. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clusters here are not as well annotated as the Berkeley clusters but I think they do the job. Again, we see a cluster for freshmen and then separate clusters for races. In addition, there’s a cluster for the Theater, Film, and Television kids (which, from as far as what I’ve seen in high school, seems about right!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s look at Harvard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/graph/harvard_annotated.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Harvard, annotated.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice there are no racial clusters! In fact, the only clusters are years and athletes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the difference between Berkeley, UCLA, and Harvard? Do people who go to Harvard just see past race? Are Berkeley and UCLA students just subconsciously segregationist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my hot take. Most colleges want to have diverse campuses and have mechanisms in place to assure this, whether its outreach to specific high schools, affirmative action, diversity offices, or scholarships. However, these efforts are focused only on the &lt;em&gt;beginning&lt;/em&gt; of the “college experience.” Colleges really have no control over what happens after a student gets to campus. At large institutions it’s easy for students to fall into a rut of only hanging out with people similar to themselves. Whereas at smaller schools the benefits of a diverse class carry throughout the entirety of college. In these environments students are constantly forced to interact with people from varied backgrounds. This is of course not to say that other benefits of diversity (increasing opportunity to those marginalized and mitigating racial and social inequality and access to higher education, among other things) are not achieved at larger schools. But many benefits (diverse perspectives and a deeper understanding of other cultures) are lost to students at a large school, simply because they aren’t ever forced out of their comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But again, maybe small schools also have this problem. As a counterpoint, consider this: Instagram connections don’t necessarily imply a strong relationship. It’s possible that at small schools small, racially homogenous cliques exist but simply aren’t picked up by the layout of the Instagram social network simply because at a small school everybody can follow everybody in their year and still have a reasonable amount of followers. In a sense, the “resolution” of an Instagram social network is a bit low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But either way, it definitely seems that the “default” state of social networks, at least large ones, is “segregated.” It’s not entirely clear to me how to solve these problems (or if these problems are actually real, or if they occur only at large schools, or also at small schools), but perhaps it’s at least a start to acknowledge and prevent evidence for the existence of this problem! Perhaps people have already pointed out and thought about this problem. If so please let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-small-aside&quot;&gt;A Small Aside&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend pointed out to me that going from elementary to middle to high school it feels like friend groups get more and more segregated (at least in American school systems in diverse schools where segregation can exist). Her assumption was that “kids don’t see race” and the fact that friend groups become more homogenous is only proof of our innocence lost. But maybe this idea of implicit segregation in large groups is an alternative explanation. After all, apparently studies show &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.utoronto.ca/news/racial-bias-may-begin-babies-six-months-u-t-research-reveals&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;babies begin developing racial biases at around six months&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps the only reason why elementary schoolers don’t split off by race is because their social circle is just too small (they spend all day with the same 25-30 kids).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;method&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recurring question from friends who graciously agreed to read the first draft of this post was “how can you be sure your analysis was correct?” I will try to address these concerns here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, this analysis was definitely not rigorous. I’m just a dude coding in his parents’ basement. I have no idea what fancy techniques sociologists use or what the latest hottest statistical machinery is. But I think these results are at least strong enough to point at some interesting things going on, perhaps things worthy of further and more rigorous analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I lay out some questions and my responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you know you scraped the entire school?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t, but I’m rather confident that I’ve gotten most of the school. In the case of Berkeley, we ended up with about 30,000 nodes. This is around the current undergrad population. This is roughly enough to account for some alumni (mostly graduation dates of ‘18 and ‘19), a percentage of Berkeley that doesn’t use Instagram (or doesn’t have very active Instagram accounts), and a number of “organization” accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you know the people you scraped actually attend the school?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained above we can look for keywords in people’s bios. For example, keywords for Berkeley included “Cal,” “Berkeley,” “UCB,” and “go bears.” We might term these users, who we are pretty confident go to Cal, as “first-order” nodes. If a node is connected to enough “first-order” nodes we could assign “second-order” status to this node, meaning we are pretty sure this node also goes to Berkeley, only because it is associated with people we know with high certainty go to Berkeley. Using this strategy we can verify social networks that we’ve scraped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How are these clusters found?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clustering algorithm uses the Louvain method to optimize the modularity of a set of clusters. The clustering algorithm is “unsupervised” in that &lt;em&gt;all it gets is the graph structure&lt;/em&gt;. That is to say, it knows nothing of usernames, parsed user bios, profile pictures, or the like. Whatever clusters it comes up with are a result of the connections alone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How is the network displayed? How do you plot the nodes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph is plotted using the “ForceAtlas2” algorithm. Perhaps a simplistic view of this algorithm is that for every node that is connected we attach an imaginary “spring” between these two nodes with some spring constant. We then relax the system and find a static configuration. This results in nodes ending up close to other nodes they are connected to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important observation is that the way we display the nodes has nothing to do with what clusters we get from the unsupervised clustering algorithm. They are two independent processes, both acting on the graph structure of the social network alone. Perhaps the fact that the clusters align with the resulting graph configuration from ForceAtlas2 is further confirmation for the validity of these clusters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem here is that we’re forced to project our graph into a two dimensional space, so we get weird situations where nodes that are part of two clusters will end up smack in the middle of the two clusters and appear not to be part of either! One potential solution is to embed the graph in higher dimensions, but anything above three dimensions (and even three dimensions) isn’t very conducive to visualization!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you label each cluster?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main ways to label clusters. The first is by parsing the bios of each person and overlying them on the graph. For example, here is Harvard with years superimposed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/graph/harv_full.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;There are obvious clusters of years here. Years usually come in pairs, one for college graduation date and one for high school.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caption: There are obvious clusters of years here. Years usually come in pairs, including college and high school graduation dates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the picture above I think it’s rather undeniable that the clusters correspond to years. Here are some example of bios that include years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;kiss plants, love people // h ‘23&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hopeful | Warren/Social Democrat | Advocate for democracy and decarceration | Casady ‘18 | Harvard ‘22 (he/him)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Seb♥️ / Harvard ‘21 / FL🌴&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;honestly just a cheese plate fan account • in vino veritas 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also use the same method as above to label clusters corresponding to sororities and fraternities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To label the other clusters I unfortunately had to resort to manually checking a subset of users from the clusters. That is, literally go on to Instagram and look at (stalk) a user’s profile. This seemed problematic, but to my great surprise almost every social group was either uniformly a single race or composed entirely of athletes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I say “uniformly a single race” I &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;uniformly&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; a single race. For example, sampling from the Berkeley asian group (right now in the middle of writing this) I find that 19/20 people are asians, with no doubt. I understand that race is a spectrum and making an assumption about somebody’s race after a brief glance at an Instagram profile ignores &lt;em&gt;so much&lt;/em&gt; about a person, but I think any reasonable person would make similar categorizations as I would. It’s a shame that I can’t show any specific profiles, or make the entire network public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athletes are much easier to classify, owing to the almost ubiquitous occurrence of a “vanity shot” (or whatever it’s called), as well as many pictures of themselves playing their sport in their uniform. In addition, a dead giveaway are these profiles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Former UC Berkeley gymnast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Professional Softballer | UC Berkeley Alum&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Le Monde ou Rien Harvard Football 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Harvard Lacrosse&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it a mistake to find the clusters first and then look for a unifying attribute? Wouldn’t this tend to lead to a biased analysis of each cluster, a sort of “confirmation bias?”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue not. In fact, Dr. John Snow undertook a similar analysis in 1854 during a cholera outbreak in London in which he first plotted out cases of cholera on a map and then traced the source to a water pump, and in the process founding modern epidemiology. What we’re doing here is not so dissimilar. We first find clusters and then try to determine what “causes” these clusters. To the point of “confirmation bias” I can only say that each cluster had an &lt;em&gt;overwhelming&lt;/em&gt; occurrence of whatever its defining attribute was and all other clusters did not. It’s a shame that I can’t show this process, because it’s quite remarkable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any closing thoughts?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day this project was just for fun and the results are far from rigorous. But that’s not to say the trends don’t exist. If anything I think it would be very interesting if a more meticulous study was done (if it hasn’t been done already!).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Berkeley Marriage Pact - Data Analysis</title>
   <link href="http://dangeng.github.io/2020/02/25/analysis/"/>
   <updated>2020-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://dangeng.github.io/blog/2020/02/25/analysis</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-berkeley-marriage-pact&quot;&gt;The Berkeley Marriage Pact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dating apps, at least it seems to me, operate on perverse incentives. Take two Tinder users who are matched together. They go on a date together, sparks fly, and love blossoms. They start dating, get married, and never open Tinder again. Years pass and the app is eventually uninstalled. In their success lies Tinder’s loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true optimal strategy for Tinder and other dating apps is to keep users swiping for as long as possible. Feed users matches who are &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; compatible. Keep them crawling back to shoot their shot. Keep them pulling on the lever of the slot machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, this was the thesis on which the Berkeley Marriage Pact was built. The idea was simple. Write a survey, have Berkeley students take it, and match people based on survey responses. And unlike dating apps, we have no ulterior motive. Our sole goal was to maximize the number of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, we had more than 3,000 responses, of which about 2500 confirmed their emails. In the end we made about 1300 matches. While the success of these matches is still not clear, we would like to present some interesting findings from the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re too lazy to read everything, I’ve organized the parts of this post that absolutely scintillate into clickbait titles for your enjoyment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#smarter&quot;&gt;Only 30% of women, 26% of Hispanics, and 27% of Blacks think they are smarter than average. 60% of men think they are smarter than average.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#depressed&quot;&gt;There seems to be a very depressed portion of Berkeley.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#extreme&quot;&gt;The more extreme your political views, the more extreme your sex life.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#choice&quot;&gt;Choice of Alcohol.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fish&quot;&gt;Fish people are the most confident.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#sex&quot;&gt;Sex.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#politics&quot;&gt;The part where we laugh at the Right.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#dunning&quot;&gt;Dunning-Kruger.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#data&quot;&gt;The Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#innocence&quot;&gt;Loss of Innocence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#sex&quot;&gt;Sex, Sexuality, and Sexual Partners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#politics&quot;&gt;Political Affiliation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#health&quot;&gt;Health and Lifestyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#smarter&quot;&gt;Are you smarter than the Average Bear?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data&quot;&gt;The Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We asked 43 questions, ranging from “religious affiliation” to “boba consumption.” All data revealed in this post will be in aggregate and no individual data should be recoverable. If you have any concerns please let us know &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:berkeleymarriagepact@gmail.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;through email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post mainly contains interesting correlations and trends in the data. You can see a presentation of just the &lt;a href=&quot;https://berkeley206399.typeform.com/report/YvzqQp/hKNOBS5tFVGJ36Y4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;aggregate responses here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/tsne.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;t-SNE visualization of survey responses. &lt;a href=&quot;https://distill.pub/2016/misread-tsne/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;We honestly have no idea what the clusters mean.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;innocence&quot;&gt;Loss of Innocence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If a body meet a body coming through the rye”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;– Rabbie Burns, “Comin thro’ the Rye”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not entirely surprising that there is a loss of innocence as people go through college, although it’s mildly interesting that we are able to quantify and graph this loss of innocence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the sexual stuff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/innocence/num_sexual_year.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/innocence/adventurousness_year.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/innocence/num_dates_year.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So all in all, people have had more sexual partners, become more sexually adventurous, and get more desperate as they grow older. It’s probably as good a time as any to point out that the error bars capture a 95% confidence interval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;choice&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;substance-abuse&quot;&gt;Substance Abuse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also take a look at various substances that people put in their bodies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/innocence/alc_choice_year.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to note that vodka preference drops drastically with age. Perhaps fueled by the &lt;em&gt;“omg I fucking love to drink, vodka is my favorite, I’m so cool”&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;“holy shit I’m literally just guzzling industrial grade solvents what am I doing with my life”&lt;/em&gt; transition that most people go through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like how “Wine” peaks in Junior year and “Beer” just keeps rising, as if people go from &lt;em&gt;“I love vodka”&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;“I’m fancy as fuck”&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;“I just don’t care anymore”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/innocence/marijuana_year.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/innocence/boba_year.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting how boba consumption drops off as well, perhaps because seniors have finally come to terms with the fact that they can’t put just anything in to their bodies. In a similar vein, it seems that people actually live healthier lifestyles as they age:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/innocence/exercise_year.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a side note, while these differences seem small you have to remember that it’s really the error bars that tell the story. While the increase in absolute days of exercise is small the error bars show that this increase &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, perhaps the saddest graph in the section, we see Berkeley slowly crushing the intellectual curiosity and academic vitality out of her students. Or at least seniors just care about things a whole lot less:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/innocence/academics_year.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sex&quot;&gt;Sex, Sexuality, and Sexual Partners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“He toss my salad like his name Romaine”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;– Nicki Minaj, “Anaconda”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My lawyers advised me not to say too much in this section, so here are some box and whisker plots (with the outliers removed):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/sex/num_sexual_gender.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the distributions for male and female:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/sex/num_sexual_gender_hist.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More boxplots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/sex/num_sexual_race.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/sex/num_sexual_religion.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/sex/num_sexual_sexuality.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;depressed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we plot out “number of sexual partners” against “importance of academics” we get an interesting trend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/sex/academics_num_sexual.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sort of sad to see that there seems to be a rather depressed portion of Berkeley students that are not only apathetic towards academics, but can’t get any sex either. You would think the relationship should be the other way around (students that don’t care about academics should have boat-loads of sex), and this is true except for the students who just don’t care about academics at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;extreme&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably one of my favorite plots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/sex/num_sexual_political.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at how beautiful this U-shape is. The underlying mechanism here is probably that politically extreme people are also extreme in other parts of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;politics&quot;&gt;Political Affiliation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“the night wind hammering about their siren scream and their mighty metal thunder!”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;– Ray Bradbury, “Fahrenheit 451”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the part of the post where we simultaneously marvel at how the Right basically writes our jokes for us and try not to be featured on “Fox and Friends.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/politics/academics_political.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/politics/num_children_political.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/politics/num_dates_political.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health and Lifestyle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“But if snow is like skin: it pulls away, so easy, dragged from the body / What if all stripped wood is branches and all frozen lakes are water?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;– Jordaan Mason, “Avalanches”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berkeley students are surprisingly healthy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/health/exercise.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/health/boba.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;smarter&quot;&gt;Are you Smarter than the Average Bear?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m smarter than the av-er-age bear!”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;– Yogi Bear&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last question we asked was “Are you smarter than the average (Cal) Bear?” 46.2% of people responded yes to this question, but things start to get interesting when you break down the results by other categories. For example, let’s start with gender. We plot the proportion of people that answered “yes” to the question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/smarter/smarter_gender.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;60% of men say they are smarter, while only 30% of women think they are smarter than average. The difference is stark. The percentages are even worse if we look at race:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/smarter/smarter_race.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;fish&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a lighter note it seems that fish-people are for some strange reason very confident:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/smarter/smarter_pet.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;dunning&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if we break the data down by “Perceived importance of academics” we get an interesting Dunning-Kruger-esque trend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/bmp/smarter/smarter_academics.png&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Berkeley Public Piano</title>
   <link href="http://dangeng.github.io/2018/08/05/berkeley-piano/"/>
   <updated>2018-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://dangeng.github.io/blog/2018/08/05/berkeley-piano</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-few-updates-april-2020&quot;&gt;A few updates (April 2020)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original post starts at &lt;a href=&quot;#overview&quot;&gt;“Overview”&lt;/a&gt;. I just thought I’d make a few updates now that it’s been about two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We originally thought the police would be annoyed at our antics. In fact, the exact opposite happened!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First I just wanted to say that most of us at the Police Department are big fans of the Public Piano. We were saddened when the last piano was vandalized and were happy to see the new one at the MLK Building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering about that last sentence. It turns out the piano was eventually vandalized, but my roommate, Josh, led the effort to replace it (if you’re counting, this would be the third piano). He got a really beautiful upright piano, painted with a landscape view of Berkeley!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/piano/new_new_piano.jpg&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Piano 3.0! &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, sometime toward the end of 2019 Josh’s piano was also destroyed. But at this point it seems the piano had actually become a sort of institution on campus. We were quickly contacted by people who wanted to replace the piano and were asking for advice. The piano was replaced almost immediately by a group of sophomores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s rather awesome to think that there’s a sort of legacy associated with the Berkeley piano now, with maybe three generation of students having taken part in maintaining its presence on Sproul!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my original post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you visit UC Berkeley you may encounter a brightly painted piano on Sproul Plaza, the main thoroughfare on the south side of campus. If you’re lucky you might hear some beautiful music from the piano. If you’re unlucky the piano may have already been removed, demolished, vandalized, or have otherwise met some unsavory end. Either way, this post is to recount the tale of how the piano ended up there in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Berkeley Public Piano was the result of much work by a close group of friends and me. This may sound sappy, but we were all united in the goal of bringing the joy of music to an otherwise dreary and sterile campus. We were tired of students walking with their headphones in and eyes on the ground, rushing to their next class or to the library to finish their homework and ignoring the world around them. We wanted people to slow down and appreciate life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inspiration&quot;&gt;Inspiration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summer of 2017 I visited Denver. There, on the 16th street mall I found brightly colored pianos on every block, free to use by anyone who wanted to. In addition to being impressed, I was slightly miffed that Berkeley did not have one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/piano/denver_piano.jpg&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;A piano from the 16th street mall &lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feedback&quot;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arriving at Berkeley after the summer, I told anybody who would listen about a potential public piano. The typical response went something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wow that sounds really cool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait, how would you get a piano?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait, who would pay for it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait, how would you transport it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait, wouldn’t it be vandalized?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait, wouldn’t it be stolen?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait, wouldn’t the administration take it away?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait, what if it rains?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently, there were many hurdles to overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acquiring-a-piano&quot;&gt;Acquiring a Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As everybody knows, the first step to putting a public piano on Sproul is to obtain a piano. And as it turns out there are many free pianos on &lt;a href=&quot;https://sfbay.craigslist.org/search/eby/sss?sort=rel&amp;amp;query=free+piano&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Craigslist&lt;/a&gt; (I’d say maybe 4-5 in East Bay every week). This is because there are many people who want to be rid of their piano but don’t want to pay to get it moved out. So they offer the piano for free under the condition that you provide transportation. I set up alerts for free pianos in east bay and waited for the free pianos to roll in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up visiting two houses with pianos. One on Albany Hill and one in the Berkeley Hills. Both pianos were utterly massive and had to be carried down a narrow flight of stairs. I gave up on both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I received an alert about a piano in Oakland. It was perfect: on wheels, easily accessible, and a short drive away. I decided to go for this one. At this point in time I was really the only person working on this project and I’m pretty sure everybody assumed I was delusional. Nevertheless, I managed to convince my roommate, Max, to come help me pick it up. I rented a U-Haul (total cost about $60) and we hauled the piano back to Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;languishing&quot;&gt;Languishing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The piano sat in our apartment for about 5 months. I blame too much school work and general indolence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inspiration-1&quot;&gt;Inspiration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With about a month left of school, I was suddenly inspired by the last minute panic that accompanies any protracted length of procrastination. Faced with the prospect of getting kicked out of my apartment and having an entire piano to deal with I decided to finally put the piano on Sproul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rallied a group of friends for the job. It was suggested that we might be ticketed or punished by the Berkeley Police Department, so we decided to sneak the piano on to campus well after midnight. At around 2 am we rolled the piano through Southside and on to Sproul plaza. It was a surprisingly fun time! It was exciting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/piano/original_piano.jpg&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;The original piano the night we put it up (Dave, worried about his future political prospects if his fingerprints were to be found on the piano by the police, had decided to wear our red over mitts which you can see right in front of him. We told him he was crazy!) &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Left to Right:&lt;/b&gt; Mimi, Allan, Daniel, David, Josh, Max, Jonas&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Photo creds:&lt;/b&gt; Richard&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;success-and-disaster&quot;&gt;Success and Disaster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The piano caused quite a stir. For three or four days it stood on Sproul plaza with people marveling at it’s mysterious appearance. Scenes like this were common:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/piano/original_piano_1.jpg&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Three separate groups of strangers, swept out of the rat-race of life to enjoy a little music and each other's company!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But alas, all good things must come to and end. As abruptly as the piano had appeared, it dissapeared. Nobody knew where it was. The theory that was floating around was that people had stolen the piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My theory is that people had simply assumed the piano was up for grabs. There was no sign to indicate that the piano was meant to be shared, nothing to imply that the piano should stay on Sproul, nor was it entirely obvious what the function of a dilapidated piano was on Sproul Plaza. Why anybody would possibly want such a crappy piano I have no idea, but I attribute this ostensibly ugly display of the dark side of human nature to a simple misunderstanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the case may be, it was evident that we had hit upon something. Here is a message we received from the person on the piano bench in the picture above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I really just wanted to reach out to say thank you guys for putting that out there. Piano throughout my life was a huge outlet, and I haven’t been able to get my hands on a real acoustic one around Berkeley in a long time. That photo was also taken about 30 minutes after I got my backpack and laptop stolen on campus; I was absolutely devastated and really needed to vent, and the piano really just happened to be there, which is something I have never seen on campus in my 7 years of being around the area. I played it that evening, and came onto campus for about an hour or so the next day and played some more, and I really think it helped me get through the past couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I know it was just a social experiment, but I just wanted to let ya know it really helped me get through a hard time. Thanks again :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was messages like these that made it clear to us that we &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to put another, better piano up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-second-chance&quot;&gt;A Second Chance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the publicity that the original piano had received, we had no trouble finding a group of people willing to sell their piano to put on Sproul. Phoebe, a Cal student, was selling one for $200 and even offered to paint it with her art friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to a new piano with a paint job, I endeavored to make it completely obvious that the piano was to be for the public. To that effect I bought some chains and a lock from Ace Hardware to tie the piano down, and also made a sign for the piano. Moreover, this second piano had no wheels making it ludicrously difficult to move (a hindrance while we attempted to move it, but an advantage in preventing it from being moved).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, at around 1 am a group of friends and I lugged the piano (on a luggage cart stolen from the basement of Unit 2) on to Sproul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/piano/new_piano.jpg&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;Take two!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Left to Right:&lt;/b&gt; Richard, Tae, Josh, Allan, Daniel, David, Thu, Mimi&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Photo creds:&lt;/b&gt; Jonas&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next couple weeks there was hardly a moment that the piano was not being played. This time, the piano stayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/public/imgs/piano/new_piano_1.jpg&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;The new piano in all it's glory! (Complete with raunchy joke on the bench)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
